Guide to the Vassar College Infirmary Registers, circa 1880s-1931
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Infirmary Registers
circa 1880s-1931
Vassar College--Infirmary
3 cubic feet (11 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Bound registers from the Vassar College Infirmary, containing logs of student and staff sick visits, symptoms, prescriptions, and treatments.
Administrative History
In its early decades, Vassar College had a small infirmary and convalescents’ room located in the southeast corner of Main Building’s fourth floor, staffed by the resident physician, her assistant, and a few nurses. As the college expanded, in 1897 the physician, Dr. Elizabeth Thelberg, rented a nearby house for eight dollars a month to accommodate more patients. Two years later, the college began negotiations with the architectural firm York and Sawyer, the architects for the recently completed Rockefeller Hall, for a more permanent medical building, to be known as Swift Infirmary in memory of Charles W. Swift.
Swift Infirmary, or "Swift Recovery" opened in 1900. Vassar’s health facilities continued to expand after the construction of Swift: first with Metcalf House, the physician’s house, in 1915—also by York and Sawyer—and later, in 1940, with Baldwin Infirmary replacing Swift, which could no longer accommodate the needs of the larger and modern college.
Source: "Swift Hall," Vassar College Encyclopedia, 2014.
Chronology of Resident Physicians, 1865-1946
Alida C. Avery, 1865-1873
Helen Worthing Webster, 1873-1881
Mary E. Allen, 1881-1884
Lucy M. Hall, 1884-1887
Elizabeth B. Thelberg, 1887-1890, 1892-1930
Gertrude A. Farwell, 1890-1892
Jane North Baldwin, 1930-1946
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 12 bound registers and one accompanying index from the Vassar College Infirmary, containing logs of student and staff sick visits, symptoms, prescriptions, and treatments.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The Vassar College Archives Files contains reports of the physician, 1870-1929, as well as photographs of some of its early physicians.
The Vassar College Biographical Files contains files on several of Vassar's early physicians, including Alida C. Avery, Helen W. Webster, Lucy M. Hall, Elizabeth B. Thelberg, and Jane North Baldwin.
.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Administration
Subjects:
Physical fitness for women; Therapeutics--Nineteenth century; Therapeutics--Twentieth century; Women--Diseases--Treatment--Nineteenth century; Women--Diseases--Treatment--Twentieth century; Women--Education; Women in medicine--Nineteenth century; Women in medicine--Twentieth century; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Places:
Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--History
Document Types:
Medical records; Registers (lists)
VCL Categories
Vassar College Administrative Offices and Functions
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, January 2023.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Container List
- Infirmary Register, circa 1880s; (32 x 15 x 4 cm) (Box 1)
- Infirmary Register, 1881-1882; (25 x 21 x 4 cm) (Box 2)
- Infirmary Register, 1882-1883; (25 x 21 x 4 cm) (Box 3)
- Infirmary Register, 1883-1884; (25 x 21 x 4 cm) (Box 4)
- Infirmary Register, 1884-1887; (35 x 30 x 5 cm) (Box 5)
- Prescription Register, 1885 September - 1887 February; (35 x 29 x 3 cm) (Box 6)
- Infirmary Register, 1892-1893; (36 x 24 x 5 cm) (Box 7)
- Infirmary Register Index, 1892-1893 (Box 7)
- Infirmary Register, 1896-1897; (33 x 18 x 4 cm) (Box 8)
- Infirmary Register, 1897-1902; (26 x 20 x 2 cm) (Box 2)
- Infirmary Register, 1909-1915; (36 x 29 x 8 cm) (Box 9)
- Infirmary Register, 1916-1921; (36 x 29 x 8 cm) (Box 10)
- Infirmary Register, 1928-1931; (37 x 32 x 9 cm) (Box 11)